Morton Gould Papers
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Morton Gould Papers 1920-1996 (bulk 1937-1995)
ML31.G68
Gould, Morton, 1913-1996
approximately 18,715 items 148 containers 64.5 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
American composer, conductor, arranger, and pianist. The collection contains music, including holograph and copyist manuscripts, printed scores, orchestral parts, lyric sheets, and sketches of Gould's compositions and arrangements; correspondence; business papers; writings; photographs; scrapbooks; programs and promotional materials related to his career; and financial and legal documents.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989--Correspondence.; Bernstein, Leonard, 1918-1990--Correspondence.; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Clinton, Bill, 1946- --Correspondence.; De Mille, Agnes--Correspondence.; Gershwin, George, 1898-1937--Correspondence.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996--Archives.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996--Correspondence.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996--Manuscripts.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996--Photographs.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996.; Gould, Morton, 1913-1996. Selections.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987--Correspondence.; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945--Correspondence.; Kostelanetz, Andre, 1901-1980--Correspondence.; Koussevitzky, Serge, 1874-1951--Correspondence.; Reagan, Ronald--Correspondence.; Robbins, Jerome--Correspondence.; Rodzinski, Artur, 1892-1958--Correspondence.; Slonimsky, Nicolas, 1894-1995--Correspondence.
Organizations
G. Schirmer, Inc.
Subjects
Composers--United States.; Motion picture music--Scores.; Music--Manuscripts--United States.; Musical--Scores and parts.; Musicals--Scores.; Television music--Scores.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Scrapbooks.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Deborah Gould, Abby Gould Burton, David Gould, and Eric Gould; 1996.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound recordings from the Morton Gould Papers have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division.
Related Material
The
USIA Artistic Ambassador Program Musical Commissions
(ML31.U72) contains a holograph manuscript of Gould's Patterns for Piano (1987).
Access and Restrictions
The Morton Gould Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1913, Dec. 10 Born, New York, N.Y.
1919 Studies piano with Ferdinand Greenwald
1920 First published composition, Just Six, for piano
1922 First radio broadcast from Bamberger’s department store in Newark, NJ
1923 Studies theory, harmony, and composition with Vincent Jones at the Institute of Musical Art (later The Juilliard School)
1928 Meets piano teacher Abby Whiteside
1929 Composes A Manhattan Rhapsody
1933 Chorale and Fugue in Jazz commissioned for Leopold Stokowski and the Philadelphia Orchestra
1933 Begins working at NBC
1935-1943 Conducts, composes, and arranges for the radio program Music for Today on WOR, New York
1936 Joins ASCAP
1936 Marries Shirly Uzin
1938, June 16 Premiere of Concerto for Piano on WOR
1939 Composes Foster Gallery at the suggestion of Fritz Reiner
1941 Conducts Spirituals at a New York festival
1941 Signs contract with Columbia Records
1942 Composes Fanfare for Freedom for Eugene Goossens
1942 Nov. Premieres American Salute on the Cresta Blanca Carnival radio show
1943 Appointed director of the Chrysler Hour on CBS
1943 Composes Symphony no. 1 for the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra and Fritz Reiner
1943 Divorces Shirley Uzin
1944 Marries Shirley Bank
1945 Appears with his orchestra in the film Delightfully Dangerous with Jane Powell
1945 Writes musical Billion Dollar Baby with Betty Comden and Adolph Green
1945 Collaborates with Jerome Robbins on Interplay
1945, Feb. 16 Son Eric born
1946 Signs contract with publisher Chappell and Co. Inc.
1947 Collaborates with Agnes de Mille on Fall River Legend
1947, Mar. 2 Son David born
1950 Writes Arms and the Girl a musical with a book by Herbert and Dorothy Fields, lyrics by Dorothy Fields, and choreography by Michael Kidd
1950, Feb. 3 Daughter Abby born
1952 Composes Tap Dance Concerto for tap dancer and orchestra
1952 Moves with wife and family to Great Neck, N.Y.
1954 Signs recording contract with RCA Records
1954, Dec. 23 Daughter Deborah born
1955 Composes Derivations for Benny Goodman and his jazz combo
1956 Declaration commissioned by WRC in Washington, D.C. for president Dwight D. Eisenhower’s second inauguration
1959 Joins board of ASCAP
1964-1965 Composes score for television documentary, World War I
1975 Signs contract with publisher G. Schirmer
1975 Composes Symphony of Spirituals
1976 Composes American Ballads
1983 Collaborates with Jerome Robbins on Astaire Variations
1984 American Sing commissioned for the summer Olympic Games held in Los Angeles
1986 Elected to the American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters
1986-1994 Serves as president of ASCAP
1992 Composes The Jogger and the Dinosaur for the Pittsburgh Youth Orchestra
1993 Composes Ghost Waltzes for the Van Cliburn International Piano Competition
1994 Receives Kennedy Center Honor
1995 Wins Pulitzer Prize for Stringmusic
1996, Feb. 21 Dies, Orlando, Fla.
Scope and Content Note
Music materials from the Morton Gould Papers span the period 1920 to 1995, with the majority dating from 1937 to 1995. The materials principally consist of holograph or copyist manuscripts, printed scores, orchestral parts, lyric sheets, and sketches of Gould's compositions and arrangements. Many of the scores, especially the photo-reproduced manuscripts, contain pencil annotations, chiefly in the hand of the composer, that indicate corrections, or, for those works conducted by Gould, performance adjustments. Works are arranged categorically by instrumentation and alphabetically by title therein. Entries indicate specific instrumentation, date of composition (if known), and commissioning organization (if applicable).
Gould's works for orchestra and band represent his most prolific output and include standouts such as American Salute and the 1995 Pulitzer Prize winnner, Stringmusic. He also composed extensively for stage, film, and television, with scores for Billion Dollar Baby (1945), Fall River Legend (1948), and documentaries Holocaust and World War I garnering national acclaim. Scores for Gould's stage and screen works are often accompanied by lyric sheets, scripts, cue sheets, and correspondence. The remaining music subseries comprise works for smaller forces (chamber and vocal), extensive titled and untitled sketches, arrangements (composed principally for and recorded by the Morton Gould Orchestra), and an assortment of works by various other composers.
Correspondence to and from Gould is arranged either chronologically by year or alphabetically by last name. The general file contains letters from friends, associates, and admirers concerning a variety of topics, such as performance logistics, publicity requests, and letters of appreciation. Gould also maintained an impressive file of personal correspondence from notable public figures, performers, and composers. Political dignitaries include presidents Dwight D. Eisenhower, Richard Nixon, Ronald Reagan, and Bill Clinton, as well as senators Al Gore, Orrin Hatch, and Edward Kennedy. Renowned composers and performers include Leonard Bernstein, Ernest Bloch, Irving Berlin, Jerome Kern, Percy Grainger, Agnes DeMille, Jascha Heifetz, Charles Ives, Eugene Ormandy, Stephen Sondheim, and many other influential figures in the history of twentieth century American performing arts.
Business papers assembled by Morton Gould and his office staff are arranged either by subject or title of composition. The majority of these work files are from the latter years of his career and cover such topics as birthday celebrations, awards, conferences, and various guest conducting appearances. Perhaps the most significant files, however, are the comprehensive G. Schirmer works lists that identify Gould's published and unpublished arrangements. The remaining subseries of business papers is dedicated exclusively to titled musical works and contains correspondence, programs, publicity materials, and notes pertaining to these pieces, including Apple Waltzes, Billion Dollar Baby, Hosedown, and The Jogger and the Dinosaur, among others.
Gould's prolific career and public appeal generated extraordinary media coverage. His appearances as composer, performer, or conductor throughout the United States and Europe for nearly seventy years are well documented in articles, interviews, programs, photographs, fliers, posters, and speeches. The Writings and Scrapbooks series principally consist of newspaper and magazine clippings arranged chronologically by year or decade. Additional materials include articles written by Gould for ASCAP, radio stations, or record companies; drafts of program notes; and interviews conducted by various organizations and universities. Related to these materials is the Promotional Materials series which contains fliers, publisher newsletters, posters, and radio broadcast schedules that further emphasize the popular reception of the composer's music at home and abroad.
Nearly five hundred photographs and slides document Gould's professional endeavors between 1938 and 1995. These mostly consist of candid shots taken at receptions, performances, and conferences, including the Van Cliburn Piano Competition (1993), Festival di George Gershwin (1968), and the premiere of The Jogger and the Dinosaur (1993). The Financial and Legal Documents series includes a variety of contracts and other materials that differ in subject matter from Gould's other business files. The last series, Artwork, contains a single 1982 drawing of Gould by artist Peter Brock.
Organization of the Morton Gould Papers
The Morton Gould Papers are organized in ten series:
Music, 1920-1995
Correspondence, 1929-1996
Business Papers, 1941-1995
Writings, 1930s-1990s
Scrapbooks, 1919-1977
Photographs, 1920s-1995
Programs, 1935-1995
Promotional Materials, 1930s-1995
Financial and Legal Documents, 1942-1995
Artwork, 1982
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006569275
Container List
- Music, 1920-1995 (Box 1-104, 146)
  - Orchestra and Band, 1934-1995
    - American ballads (orchestra), 1975, Scores, sketches; Comissioned by the New York State Arts Council and the U.S. Bicentennial Society of Richmond, VA for the Queens Symphony Orchestra of New York; Other title: Bicentennial ballads (Box-folder 1/1-3, 73/1)
    - American concertette no. 2 (viola, band), 1944, Scores, sketches; Other title: Concertette for viola (Box-folder 1/4-5)
    - American salute (on "Johnny comes marching home") (orchestra), 1943, Score (Box-folder 73/2)
    - American sing (voices, orchestra), 1984, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 2/1, 93/1)
    - Anniversary quadrille (orchestra), 1954, Scores; For Vladimir Golschmann and the St. Louis Symphony Orchestra's 75th anniversary (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Ballad for band, 1946, Scores (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Bell fugue (orchestra), 1939, Scores; For Paul Whiteman concert at Carnegie Hall (Box-folder 93/2)
    - Big city blues (orchestra), 1950, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 73/3)
    - Broadway (piano, orchestra), 1931, Score (Box-folder 103/1)
    - Burchfield gallery (orchestra), 1979, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by the Charles E. Burchfield Foundation (Box-folder 2/4-5, 3/1-3)
    - Calypso souvenir (orchestra), 1964, Scores; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 73/4)
    - Centennial symphony (band), 1983, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program note, program; Commissioned by the University of Texas Longhorn Band; Other title: Gala for band (Box-folder 3/4-5, 93/3)
    - Cheers!: a celebration march (orchestra, optional organ), 1979, Score; Commissioned by the Boston Symphony for Arthur Fiedler's 50th season as conductor of the Boston Pops (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Chorale and fugue in jazz (2 pianos, orchestra), 1934, Scores (Box-folder 73/5)
    - Chorales and rags (orchestra), 1977; orchestrated 1982, Score; Originally composed as the ballet, Audubon (Box-folder 73/6)
    - Classical variations (on colonial themes) (orchestra), 1985, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence, program clippings; Commissioned by the Pittsburgh Post Gazette (Box-folder 4/2, 73/7)
    - Columbia: broadsides for orchestra on Columbian themes, 1967, Score; Laid in: correspondence, title page from conductor's score; Commissioned by Howard Mitchell and the Washington National Symphony (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Columbia fanfares (brass), 1967, Scores (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Concerto for flute and orchestra, 1984, Scores, parts, sketches; Laid in: correspondence, program, press clippings, program notes; Commissioned by Katherine Lewis for Donald Peck, Sir George Solti, and the Chicago Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 4/5-6, 5/1-3, 93/4)
    - Concerto for orchestra, 1945, Score, sketches; Commissioned by the Cleveland Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 5/4, 94/1)
    - Concerto for piano (piano, orchestra), 1938, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 5/5-6, 6/1, 74/1)
    - Concerto for viola, 1943-1945, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 6/2-3, 74/2)
    - Concerto for violin, 1938, Scores, parts, sketches (Box-folder 7/1-2)
    - Conga (band), undated, Score (Box-folder 74/3)
    - Cowboy rhapsody (orchestra), 1944, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 7/3, 94/2)
    - Dance gallery. Soft shoe gavotte (orchestra), undated, Score, sketches; Incomplete (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Dance variations (2 pianos, orchestra), 1953, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence, photocopy of album cover; see also Rib of Eve (Box-folder 7/5, 74/4)
    - Declaration (2 speakers, speaking men's chorus, orchestra), 1956, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program notes, program; Commissioned by stations WRC and WRC-TV of NBC (Box-folder 7/6, 74/5, 75/1)
    - Declaration suite (orchestra), 1957, Score (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Derivations (clarinet, band), 1955; revised 1963 and 1965, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 8/2-4, 75/2-3)
    - Dialogues (piano, string orchestra), 1958, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 8/5, 9/1)
    - Diversions (tenor saxophone, orchestra), 1990, Scores, saxophone part, sketches; For James Houlik; Commissioned by Carillon Importers on behalf of Absolut Vodka (Box-folder 9/2-5, 76/1)
    - Elegy for strings, 1978, Scores (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Family album. Old romance; Horseless carriage galop; The open trolley (band), 1951, Scores; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Fanfare for freedom (wind ensemble), 1943, Scores, parts; For Eugene Goossens and the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Fanfare to James Whitcomb Riley (brass, percussion), 1949, Scores, parts; Laid in: program; For Wolf Trap's 20th anniversary and Catherine Shouse's 95th birthday (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Festive music (orchestra), 1964, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by the Tri-City Symphony, Davenport, Iowa, for their 50th anniversary (Box-folder 10/4-5)
    - Flares and declamations (orchestra), 1987, Scores; For the opening concert of the American Symphony Orchestra 25th anniversary season (Box-folder 76/2)
    - Flourishes and galop (orchestra), 1983, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence; Commissioned for the grand opening of the Kentucky Center for the Arts for the Louisville Orchestra (Box-folder 10/6, 76/3)
    - Folk suite (orchestra), 1941, Scores; For the High School of Music and Art, New York City (Box-folder 76/4)
    - Formations: for marching band, 1964, Score, sketches; Commissioned by the University of Florida Gator Band (Box-folder 10/7, 76/5)
    - Foster gallery (orchestra), 1939, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program notes; For Fritz Reiner (Box-folder 10/8, 77/1)
    - Global greeting (band), 1994, Scores, parts; Laid in: program; In honor of the International Confederation of Societies of Authors and Composers 30th world congress (Box-folder 11/1, 77/2)
    - Guajira. Dance seven (clarinet, orchestra), 1949, Score, clarinet part, sketches (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Hail to a First Lady (brass, percussion), 1991, Score, parts; Laid in: program notes; For Barbara Bush (Box-folder 11/3)
    - Harvest (harp, vibraphone, string orchestra), 1945, Scores, sketches; For Shirley Gould (Box-folder 11/4-5)
    - Holiday music (orchestra), 1947, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 11/6, 77/3)
    - Holiday music (band), 1947, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 12/1-2)
    - A homespun overture (orchestra), 1939, Score, sketches (Box-folder 12/3)
    - The hoofer suite (tap dancer, orchestra), 1956, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 12/4, 77/4)
    - Hosedown (narrator, orchestra), 1995, Scores, sketches; Laid in: text, correspondence; Commissioned by the Pittsburgh Symphony Association for the Pittsburgh Youth Orchestra (Box-folder 12/5, 77/5)
    - Housewarming (orchestra), 1982, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by the Baltimore Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 12/6, 78/1)
    - Inventions (4 pianos, band), 1953, Score; For Steinway and Sons centennial (Box-folder 78/2)
    - Jekyll and Hyde variations (orchestra), 1956, Scores, sketches; For Dmitri Mitropoulos (Box-folder 12/7, 13/1, 78/3)
    - The jogger and the dinosaur (rapper, orchestra), 1992, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by the Pittsburgh Symphony Association for the Pittsburgh Youth Orchestra (Box-folder 13/2-3, 78/4)
    - Lincoln legend (orchestra), 1941, Scores (Box-folder 78/5)
    - Little symphony, undated, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 14/1, 78/6)
    - A Manhattan rhapsody (orchestra), 1929, Scores; Multiple versions (Box-folder 146/1)
    - Minstrel show (orchestra), 1946, Score, sketches (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Minute and waltz rag (orchestra), 1990, Scores; Commissioned by the Baltimore Symphony for its 75th anniversary (Box-folder 79/1)
    - Notes of remembrance (orchestra), 1989, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program notes; For the American Symphony Orchestra League, in memory of Ralph Black (Box-folder 14/3-4, 79/2)
    - Philharmonic waltzes (orchestra), 1948, Score (Box-folder 14/5)
    - Poem for orchestra no. 1, 1928, Score (Box-folder 103/2)
    - Prisms (band), 1962, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence, instrumentation list; For the College Band Directors National Association (Box-folder 14/6, 79/3)
    - Red Cavalry march (orchestra), 1943, Score (Box-folder 79/4)
    - Remembrance day: soliloquy for a passing century (wind ensemble), 1995, Scores, sketches; Laid in: press clipping, correspondence; Commissioned by the University of Connecticut and the Raymond and Beverly Sackler Foundation (Box-folder 14/7, 79/5)
    - Rhythm gallery (narrator, orchestra), 1958, Scores, narrator part; Laid in: list of corrections; For Tom Scherman and the Little Orchestra Society (Box-folder 15/1-3, 79/6)
    - Rhythmic prelude (orchestra), undated, Score, parts (Box-folder 15/4)
    - Rumbolero (orchestra), 1934, Score, parts (Box-folder 15/5)
    - St. Lawrence suite: commemoration music for band, 1958, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by the Hydro Electric Power Commission of Ontario and the Power Authority of the State of New York (Box-folder 16/1-2)
    - Salutations (narrator, concert band), 1966, Scores, sketches; For David Sarnoff (Box-folder 16/3-4)
    - Santa Fe saga (concert band), 1956, Scores, sketch; For Edwin Franko Goldman (Box-folder 16/5, 80/1)
    - Serenade of carols (band), 1949, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 16/6)
    - Showpiece (orchestra), 1954, Score, sketches (Box-folder 17/1, 80/2)
    - Soundings (orchestra), 1969, Score, sketches; Laid in: program notes, program; Commissioned by the Junior League of Atlanta for Robert Shaw and the Atlanta Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 17/2-3)
    - Spirituals: for orchestra, 1940, Score, sketches (Box-folder 17/4)
    - Spirituals: for strings, 1961, Score; Laid in: program notes, program (Box-folder 17/5)
    - Stringmusic, 1993, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program; Commissioned by the National Symphony Orchestra through a grant from the Hechinger Foundation, Hechinger Fund for New Orchestral Works (Box-folder 17/6-8)
    - Suite no. 1 for orchestra, piano, and solo instruments, 1928, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 17/9)
    - Symphonette no. 2: American symphonette, 1938; arranged 1939, Scores, piano arrangement; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 18/1, 80/3)
    - Symphonette no. 3: American symphonette, 1937?, Scores, sketches; Laid in: correspondence (Box-folder 80/4)
    - Symphonette no. 4: Latin-American, 1940, Score, sketch (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Symphony, undated, Score (Box-folder 18/3)
    - Symphony, 1937, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 18/4-6, 80/4)
    - Symphony for band, 1952, Scores, sketches; For the West Point Sesquicentennial Celebration (Box-folder 19/1-2)
    - Symphony of spirituals, 1975, Scores, sketches; Laid in: program notes, program; Commissioned by the Detroit Symphony Orchestra through a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts in celebration of the U.S. bicentennial (Box-folder 19/3-4, 20/1-2)
    - Symphony no. 1, 1942, Score (Box-folder 81/1)
    - Symphony no. 2, 1944, Score; Commissioned by the YMCA for its centennial; Other title: Symphony on marching tunes (Box-folder 94/3)
    - Symphony no. 3, 1946-1947, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 20/3, 81/2-3)
    - Tap dance concerto (tap dancer, orchestra), 1952, Scores, tap dancer part, sketches; Laid in: program notes (Box-folder 21/1-2)
    - Tropical (orchestra), 1938, Score, violin part (Box-folder 21/3)
    - Troubadour music (4 guitars, orchestra), 1968; revised 1971, Scores, sketches; For the Romeros, in commemoration of the 200th anniversary of the founding of San Diego (Box-folder 21/4, 82/1)
    - Variations for piano and small orchestra, undated, Score (Box-folder 103/3)
    - Venice (double orchestra, brass choirs), 1966, Scores, sketches; Commissioned by Milton Katims for the Seattle Symphony Orchestra (Box-folder 21/5, 22/1, 82/2)
    - Vivaldi gallery (string quartet, divided orchestra), 1968, Scores (Box-folder 22/2, 82/3)
    - White lights (orchestra), undated, Score (Box-folder 103/4)
  - Stage Works, 1945-1983
    - Arms and the girl (musical), 1949, Scores, sketches (Box-folder 22/3-5, 23/1)
    - Astaire variations (ballet), 1983, Scores, parts, sketches; Laid in: movement list, timing sheets; Other title: I’m old fashioned (Box-folder 23/2-4, 24/1-2, 82/4, 83/1)
    - AT&T ride "Hello song" (World's Fair amusement ride), 1964, Scores, sketches; Laid in: timing sheets, correspondence, contact list (Box-folder 24/2-4, 83/2)
    - Apple waltzes (ballet), 1969, Scores, sketches; Laid in: list of common apple varietals (Box-folder 24/5, 84/1-2)
    - Billion dollar baby (musical), 1945, Scores, sketches; Laid in: script, correspondence (Box-folder 25/1-3, 26/1)
    - Billion dollar baby (musical). I'm sure of your love, 1945, Score (Box-folder 84/3)
    - Desire (musical), undated, Scores, sketches; Laid in: script, synopsis; Incomplete, never produced (Box-folder 26/2)
    - Enter Juliet (musical), 1978-1979, Scores, sketches; Laid in: scripts, correspondence, clippings; Never produced (Box-folder 26/3-5, 27, 28/1-2)